Register of the Uncommon Knowledge Video Tapes
Hoover Institution Archives
- Individual Program Descriptions, 1996-2010 (Folder 1-60, 62-126, on shelf)
  - Web, 2009
    - "Crisis and the Law with Richard Epstein" No. WUK09_07, 2009 March 23 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 113; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Considered one if the most influential legal thinkers of modern times, Richard Epstein, the Peter and Kirsten Bedford Senior Fellow at the Hoover Institution, brings his libertarian views to bear on the current financial crisis-"government incentives were perverse, so the actions of the private parties were perverse"-and rates the performances of George Bush and Barack Obama in their responses to the crisis. He speaks to the importance of contracts and the constitutionality of the "expo facto" taxation on AIG executives and the Employee Free Choice Act embraced by President Obama. Finally he speaks of his personal and professional dealings with Barack Obama when they were law school faculty mates at the University of Chicago.
    - "At War with General Jack Keane" No. WUK09_08, 2009 March 25 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 113; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      During his thirty-seven years in the U.S. Army, Jack Keane earned four stars. Beginning his career as a paratrooper in Vietnam, he rose to command both the 101st Airborne Division and the 18th Airborne Corps. In his final post he served as the Army's vice chief of staff. General Keane retired from active duty in 2003. In 2006, General Keane and military historian Frederick Kagan helped develop a new approach to the Iraq war that would become known as "the surge." How did we arrive at that point in 2006 when the entire war effort in Iraq hung in the balance - why did the war go so badly for so long? General Keane gives an insider's account of this pivotal time in the Iraq war and of the resistance encountered within the military to that dramatic change in strategy. Keane discusses the lessons to be learned from the Iraq War and how to define and achieve victory in Afghanistan. Finally, he deals with the overall question of the military force structure and the danger of becoming preoccupied with the threat of terrorism and insurgencies and thus risking being unable to confront a conventional power.
    - "The Aussie Way with John Howard" No. WUK09_09, 2009 April 23 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 113; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Prime Minister Howard offers insights into Australia's own "special relationship" with the United States beginning with why Australia's participation in the Iraq war was in his nation's best interest. Echoing parallels with the United States, he offers his views on multiculturalism-which he calls "a very confused credo"-and Australia's role in the "Anglosphere," particularly as it relates to China, its largest and most powerful Asian neighbor. He speaks of the current financial crisis and the need to remain confident in the market and the dangers of overregulation. Finally, he answers "What should Americans know about Australia that we don't?"
    - "The Environment with Steven Hayward" No. WUK09_10, 2009 April 30 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 114; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Hayward challenges the established narrative of environmentalism, beginning with the notion that the earth is fragile and that we have little time to save it from environmental catastrophe. He deconstructs the case for global warming (including "cap and trade" plans to limit greenhouse gas emissions and the new EPA "endangerment finding" on CO2) and speaks to the challenges faced by poor countries as they seek to modernize and at the same time reduce the pollution that has historically accompanied modernization. Finally, he offers his insights into the deep structure of environmentalism that substitutes a human apocalypse for a religious one.
    - "The Politics of Hollywood with Andrew Breitbart" No. WUK09_11, 2009 May 5 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 114; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Identified as "one of the ten most important people in the media that nobody's ever met," Andrew Breitbart details why leftward-leaning Hollywood is dangerous for America and why the people who run it are "uninteresting," "vitriolic," and "vicious." Segueing from Hollywood to the Internet, Breitbart explores why the right dominates talk radio and the left seems to do better on the Internet and how the decline of print media is changing the nature of the national political conversation.
    - "Charles Kesler on the Grand Liberal Project" No. WUK09_12, 2009 May 28 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 114; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      In a sweeping review of American political history, Kesler outlines the "grand liberal project" begun a century ago. It is a project, he asserts, that has expressed itself in three distinct waves: political liberalism, economic liberalism, and cultural liberalism. Kesler further maintains that Barack Obama seeks nothing less than to complete and perfect this project. Finally, he confronts the issues of how conservatism lost its way in the face of the liberal project and how it might regain its initiative.
    - "Africa with Dambisa Moyo" No. WUK09_13, 2009 June 12 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 114; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      During the past fifty years, more than $1 trillion in development-related aid has been transferred from rich countries to Africa. Moyo asserts, however, that this assistance has made African people no better off. "Africa's real per capita income today is lower than in the 1970s, with over half of the 700 million Africans living on less than a dollar a day." Eschewing the "glamour aid" of celebrities such as Bob Geldof and Bono, she argues that the key to transforming African countries is to make them less reliant on foreign aid and compel them to "enforce rules of prudence and not live beyond their means."
    - "Housing with Thomas Sowell" No. WUK09_14, 2009 June 29 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 115; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Thomas Sowell analyzes the recent housing boom and bust, beginning with the underlying economic causes that artificially inflated housing costs in certain markets. He points the finger directly at political decisions in Washington - particularly involving Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac - that enabled and promoted the financing of an unsustainable housing bubble in which the collapse of prices in a few inflated markets rapidly evolved into a national crisis. Sowell challenges the accepted wisdom of modeling a recovery based on the New Deal, which he asserts did little to help - and perhaps even extended - The Great Depression. Finally, he disputes the value of the recent stimulus package and argues against Obama's health-care and energy initiatives.
    - "Lincoln with Harry Jaffa" No. WUK09_15, 2009 July 13 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 115; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      In a year that marks the two hundredth year since the birth of Lincoln, and the fiftieth year since the publication of his own Crisis of the House Divided, Harry Jaffa discusses Lincoln as a thinker and philosopher as well as the great import of the Lincoln-Douglas debates and their lasting influence on American society. Jaffa explains that the Lincoln-Douglas debates centered on the "question of whether the people make the moral law or the moral law makes the people." At the core of Lincoln's political philosophy, Jaffa argues, was the proposition from the Declaration of Independence that "all men are created equal." And it is this proposition that gives Americans alone, Jaffa says, a legitimate claim to a belief that their country is truly exceptional.
    - "Trotsky per Hitchens and Service" No. WUK09_16, 2009 July 28 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 115; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Leon Trotsky, one of the leading figures of the Russian October Revolution, remains a controversial figure. For many, Trotsky's assassination in Mexico marked a tragedy in Soviet history, cutting off the possibility of a humane version of communism taking hold in Russia, with Trotsky himself arguing that he would have held back the tides of arbitrary rule and terror. But is that so? In answering this question and others about Trotsky's ideas, political defeat, and exile, Hitchens and Service speak to the very nature of communist ideology.
    - "Lincoln and More with Harry Jaffa, part II" No. WUK09_17, 2009 July 14 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 115; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      In a previous Uncommon Knowledge interview, Jaffa discussed his classic Crisis of the House Divided. In this interview, Jaffa returns to discuss the sequel, A New Birth of Freedom. He begins by making a critical point: whereas the Founders had expected slavery simply to wither away, by the middle of the nineteenth century the peculiar institution had done no such thing. The Civil War, Jaffa insists, was a necessary war-an unavoidable war-not a war of choice. When the war broke out, anyone who had engaged in a cool calculation of the odds would have put his money on the Confederacy, not the Union. Commenting on contemporary America, Jaffa points out the distinction between the "immutable principles of private morality" that President Washington spoke of and the "fundamental American values" that President Obama speaks of today. "Values are moral choices, which have no object or basis," Jaffa asserts. "The value is a subjective desire, not an objective truth. A hundred years ago, nobody would have spoken about our principles as being values."
    - "GOP Principles with Thaddeus McCotter" No. WUK09_18, 2009 August 24 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 116; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Why has the GOP stumbled in the new century, and what can it do to restore itself? Rep. McCotter analyzes how the Republican Party went off track, taking on today's big issues-the bailouts and the economy, health care, and the war in Afghanistan-to offer insights into how the GOP can regain the confidence of the American people. Switching from issues to ideology, McCotter spells out the principles of conservatism that the party must not compromise as it changes to meet the challenges of the future.
    - "The Age of Reagan with Steven Hayward" No. WUK09_19, 2009 August 21 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 116; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Discussing his new book, The Age of Reagan: The Conservative Counterrevolution, Hayward asserts that Ronald Reagan was one of the most consequential presidents in American history. In foreign affairs, he presents Reagan as possessing unique insights into issues that had confounded the policy establishment for decades and as willing to battle not only with the Democratic opposition but also with the conventional reflexes of much of his own party and staff. Against prevailing opinion, Hayward defends his proposition that Reagan's domestic record is commensurate with his foreign achievements: "One person saved the Reagan Revolution from retreat and rout. That person was Ronald Reagan." Finally, Hayward argues that, "if Reagan failed in a permanent alignment the way Roosevelt did with the New Deal, it was because the Republican Party, its successors, and even Reagan himself were not a full-fledged constitutional movement." Just what would such a constitutional movement look like today?
    - "The Law and More with Judge Laurence Silberman" No. WUK09_20, 2009 August 5 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 116; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      In Parker v. the District of Columbia, Judge Silberman wrote the 2007 opinion striking down parts of the District of Columbia's ban on handguns as unconstitutional. Here he explains how his thinking about the Second Amendment evolved "When the case first came to me, I had been under the impression...that the Second Amendment [the right to bear arms] was a collective right. When I looked into it, I concluded to the contrary." Silberman further advances the "theory of originalism" and defends the positions he staked out 30 years ago when he published a famous essay titled "Will Lawyering Strangle Democratic Capitalism?" Finally, as one of the principals of the Robb/Silberman Commission, he takes on the assertion that "Bush lied, people died," labeling it "an absurd and outrageous libel."
    - "Health Care Reform with David Brady and Daniel Kessler" No. WUK09_21, 2009 October 6 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 116; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Brady and Kessler combine the insights of a political scientist with those of an economist and offer unique observations into the political forces and policies at play in the current health care debate. Brady and Kessler compare the politics of Clintoncare in 1993 to the politics of Obamacare today. If President Clinton couldn't push through sweeping health care reform in 1993 why does President Obama think he can in 2009? Has public opinion or the health care system changed? Has the health care system itself changed? And what exactly is the substance of the president's plan and will Congress give him what he wants?
    - "The Iran Problem with Hanson and Baer" No. WUK09_22, 2009 October 20 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 117; DVD MPEG4, box 120)
      Does Iran possess the ability to produce nuclear weapons? Both Bob Baer and Victor Hanson agree that it does. On the questions that flow from this assertion, agreement is more difficult to find. What does Iran hope to accomplish by developing the bomb? Can the United States live with a nuclear Iran-can Israel? Israeli defense minister Ephraim Sneh in an October interview asserted that "if no crippling sanctions are in place by Christmas, Israel will strike....If we are left alone, we will act alone." Does Israel possess the ability to destroy the Iranian nuclear program? With each month bringing another deception and diversion from Iran, what can the United States do to prevent a conflagration in the Middle East?
    - "The World with Vÿclav Klaus" No. WUK09_23, 2009 November 6 (Folder DVCPro, box 118; DVCPro, box 118; DVCPro, box 118; DVCPro, box 118; DVD MPEG4, box 120;)
      In retelling his experience of living through the Velvet Revolution, the fall of the Berlin Wall, and the lifting of the Iron Curtain, Czech Republic president Vÿclav Klaus offers his views on what students today need to understand about life under communism. He also defends his opposition to the idea of a European superstate-"I do not consider the Lisbon Treaty to be a good thing for Europe, for the freedom of Europe, or for the Czech Republic"-and compares the ideology of environmentalism and global warming alarmism with the ideology of communism. Finally, he ponders the question of what lessons from history his grandchildren are learning.
    - "Soft Despotism with Paul Rahe" No. WUK09_24, 2009 November 19 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 117; DVD MPEG4, box 120; DVD Flash, box 120)
      Paul Rahe discusses the danger a consolidation of government poses for the people of the United States, the psychological disposition that makes democratic peoples vulnerable to servile temptation, and the institutions that once in some measure shielded Americans from these propensities. Asserting that the Obama administration is pursuing tyrannical ambitions, he offers some of the reasons why it is now possible for us to recover the liberty that once was ours.
    - "Insights with Rene Girard" No. WUK09_25, 2009 December 1 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 117; DVD MPEG4, box 120; DVD Flash, box 120)
      First describing the triangular structure of desire-object, model, and subject-Girard tells how conflicts are resolved and why human society is not marked by total conflict all the time. He further speaks of the intersection of the universal themes of mythology and Christianity and Christianity's future. "History...is a test of mankind," says Rene Girard, and "mankind is failing that test."
  - Collections, 1996-1999
    - "Domestic Policy" Collection 1, 1996 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 44; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 44)
      Includes episodes UK1_1; UK1_2; UK1_6; UK1_12
    - "Foreign Policy" Collection 2, 1996 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 44; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 44)
      Includes episodes UK1_3; UK1_9; UK1_5; UK1_10
    - "Cultural Issues" Collection 3, 1996 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 45; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 45)
      Includes episodes UK1_11; UK1_4; UK1_13; UK1_8
    - "Foreign Policy" Collection 4, 1997 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 45; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 45)
      Includes episodes UK103; UK113; UK112: UK107
    - "Politics and Economics" Collection 5, 1997 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 46; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 46)
      Includes episodes UK106; UK101; UK104; UK109
    - "Social Welfare" Collection 6, 1997 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 46; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 46)
      Includes episodes UK111; UK110; UK108; UK102; UK105
    - "Beyond Our Borders" Collection 7, 1998 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 47; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 47)
      Includes episodes UK201; UK202; UK211; UK210
    - "Within Our Borders" Collection 8, 1998 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 47; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 47)
      Includes episodes UK204; UK203; UK213; UK206; UK209
    - "Challenging Our Borders" Collection 9, 1998 (Folder VHS, box 26; Betacam SP (pt. 1), box 48; Betacam SP (pt. 2), box 48)
      Includes episodes UK208; UK205; UK207; UK212
    - "Establishing the Rules" Collection 10, 1999 (Folder VHS, box 26)
      Includes episodes UK304; UK312: UK301; UK305
    - "Breaking the Rules" Collection 11, 1999 (Folder VHS, box 26)
      Includes episodes UK306; UK307; UK302; UK310; UK311
    - "Are There Rules?" Collection 12, 1999 (Folder VHS, box 26)
      Includes episodes UK303; UK308; UK309; UK313
    - "An International View" Collection 13, 1999 (Folder VHS, box 26)
      Includes episodes UK322; UK320; UK314; UK317; UK319
    - "A Libertarian View" Collection 14, 1999 (Folder VHS, box 26)
      Includes episodes UK324; UK325; UK315; UK326
    - "A Vision of Reform" Collection 15, 1999 (Folder VHS, box 26)
      Includes episodes UK316; UK323; UK318; UK321
  - Web, 2010
    - "Thomas Sowell discusses his new book Intellectuals and Society" WUK10_01, 2009 December 11 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 121)
    - "Crisis and Command with John Yoo" No. WUK10_02, 2009 December 18 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 121)
      John Yoo
    - "Are We All Keynesians Now?" No. WUK10_03, 2010 January 25 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 121)
      Richard Epstein; John Taylor
    - "Business and the media with Rupert Murdoch" No. WUK10_04, 2010 February 05 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 121)
      Rupert Murdoch
    - "Fox and more with Roger Ailes" alternate title: The Man Who Invented Fox News" WUK10_05, 2010 February 05 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 121)
      Roger Ailes
    - "Victor Davis Hanson -- War and History, Ancient and Modern" No. WUK10_06, 2010 March 09 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 122)
      Victor Davis Hanson
    - "New rules of war with Hanson and Arquilla" No. WUK10_07, 2010 March 19 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 122)
      "Victor Davis Hanson John Arquilla"
    - "The End of the World as We Know It" No. WUK10_08, 2010 April 26 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 122)
      Mark Steyn
    - "The United States and the Middle East" No. WUK10_09, 2010 April 27 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 122)
      Fouad Ajami
    - "John Podhoretz: The Purposes of Political Combat" No. WUK10_10, 2010 April 29 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 122)
      John Podhoretz
    - "War with Sebastian Junger" No. WUK10_11, 2010 May 25 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 123)
      Sebastian Junger
    - "Mark Steyn and Rob Long: The Gipper Then and Now" No. WUK10_12, 2010 April 26 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 123)
      Mark Steyn and Rob Long
    - "Economic Headwinds with Lazear and Boskin" No. WUK10_13, 2010 June 12 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 123)
      Michael J. Boskin and Edward Paul Lazear
    - "Charles Hill: Grand Strategies" No. WUK10_14, 2010 July 14 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 124)
      Charles Hill
    - "Forty Years of American Politics: Michael Barone" No. WUK10_15, 2010 August 02 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 124)
      Michael Barone
    - "Thomas Sowell - Dismantling America" No. WUK10_16, 2010 August 06 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 124)
    - "Politics with Haley Barbour" No. WUK10_17, 2010 August 20 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 124)
      Haley Barbour
    - "Harvey Mansfield: The Left on Campus" No. WUK10_18, 2010 August 09 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 125)
      Harvey Mansfield
    - "Thatcher & More with Claire Berlinski" No. WUK10_19, 2010 September 03 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 125)
      Claire Berlinski
    - "The New Old World Order" No. WUK10_20, 2010 October 04 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 125)
    - "The New Road to Serfdom: A Letter of Warning to America" No. WUK10_21, 2010 October 17 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 125)
      Daniel Hannan
    - "The Economist's Economist" No. WUK10_22, 2010 October 28 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 126)
      Gary Becker
    - "The State in the Third Millenium" No. WUK10_23, 2010 November 09 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 126)
      Prince Hans Adam
    - "The Rational Optimist" No. WUK10_24, 2010 November 18 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 126)
      Matt Ridley
    - "Basic Economics" No. WUK10_25, 2010 December 14 (Folder Digital Betacam, box 126)
- Incremental Materials (Box 127)